ALEX STEIN

Github: alexstein0 \diamond Google Scholar \diamond X profile: alex_stein0

 $(561) \cdot 779 \cdot 7949 \diamond astein@umd.edu$

RESEARCH OVERVIEW

My research interests cover a range of machine learning topics, including but not limited to: LLM reasoning, adversarial attacks, efficient inference using adaptive compute. I am especially interested in exploring the extent to which LLMs understand context and generalize beyond their training data.

EDUCATION

PhD Candidate in Computer Science

College Park, MD

 $University\ of\ Maryland$

August 2021 - Present

· Advised by Prof. Tom Goldstein and Prof. John Dickerson

Masters of Science, Computer Science

College Park, MD

 $University\ of\ Maryland$

Dec 2024

· GPA: 3.8

Columbia University

New York City, NY

BS Computer Science: Machine Learning Concentration

May 2016

· Minor: Operations Research

EMPLOYMENT EXPERIENCE

Capital One

McLean, VA

Applied Research PhD Intern, Behavioral Modeling Team

June 2024-Aug 2024

· Applied Researcher focused on transformers for temporal tabular data tasks such as event prediction and time series

University of Maryland

College Park, MD

Research Assistant

May 2022-Present

· Research assistant in Tom Goldstein's lab exploring the ways in which language models reason in long context settings and other length-generalization tasks

RBC Capital Markets

New York City, NY

VP, Quantitative Researcher and Development, Global Equities

Aug 2016-Dec 2021

- · Created alpha signals used to predict market direction
- · Trained predictive models used in production systems for scheduling, liquidity seeking, and routing algorithms
- · Co-lead rewrite of entire trading system, personally contributing over 10,000 lines of code

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Maryland

College Park, MD

Teacher's Assistant

- · Analysis of Algorithms (Fall 2021)
- · Introduction to Machine Learning (Spring 2022)

TECHNICAL SKILLS, CERTIFICATES AND AWARDS

Computer Languages Python, Java, Matlab, LATEX, Q/kDB+

ML Frameworks Pytorch, Huggingface, Lightning, Pandas, Numpy

Github https://github.com/alexstein0

Dean and Chair Fellowship Aug 2021–May 2023 FINRA qualifications exams Series 7, 57, 63

TALKS

Featurespace research seminar: Event Prediction using Autoregressive Transformers

UMD ML research group: Intro to Event Prediction using Transformers

Nov 2024
Capital One AI research symposium: Event Prediction with Autoregressive Transformers

Aug 2024
Capital One Behavioral Modeling research group: Event Prediction

July 2024

PAPERS AND PREPRINTS

A Simple Baseline for Predicting Events with Auto-Regressive Tabular Transformers

Alex Stein, Samuel Sharpe, Doron Bergman, Senthil Kumar, C. Bayan Bruss, John Dickerson, Tom Goldstein, and Micah Goldblum

arXiv preprint arXiv:2410.10648

Coercing LLMs to do and reveal (almost) anything

Jonas Geiping, **Alex Stein**, Manli Shu, Khalid Saifullah, Yuxin Wen, and Tom Goldstein arXiv preprint arXiv:2402.14020

Transformers Can Do Arithmetic with the Right Embeddings

Sean McLeish, Arpit Bansal, **Alex Stein**, Neel Jain, John Kirchenbauer, Brian R. Bartoldson, Bhavya Kailkhura, Abhinav Bhatele, Jonas Geiping, Avi Schwarzschild, and Tom Goldstein

The Thirty-eighth Annual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems

Running Huge Context Windows On Tiny GPUs

Monte Hoover, Ryan Synk, Neel Jain, John Kirchenbauer, Alex Stein, Manli Shu, Ramani Duraiswami, and Tom Goldstein

Under Review, arXiv pending. Under Review

Algorithm Design for Learned Algorithms

Avi Schwarzschild, Sean Michael McLeish, Arpit Bansal, Gabriel Diaz, **Alex Stein**, Aakash Chandnani, Aniruddha Saha, Richard Baraniuk, Long Tran-Thanh, Jonas Geiping, and Tom Goldstein arXiv pending

What Algorithms do Machines Learn to Solve Mazes?

Avi Schwarzschild, Arpit Bansal, Sean McLeish, **Alex Stein**, and Tom Goldstein arXiv pending

Neural Auctions Compromise Bidder Information

Alex Stein, Avi Schwarzschild, Michael Curry, Tom Goldstein, and John Dickerson arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.00116

Deadpool: a Deeper, Darker, Dark Pool from Horizontally Scalable Parallel MPC for databases Alex Stein, Kamil Doruk Gur, and Ian Miers arXiv pending

EDM: Extracted Descriptions of Music from Generative Models

Gowthami Somepalli, Khalid Saifullah, Hamid Kazemi, **Alex Stein**, Arpit Bansal, David Miller, Micah Goldblum, and Tom Goldstein arXiv pending